<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The evil of our dayes with the remedy of it : a sermon preach'd at a visitation at Rothwell in Northamptonshire, Octob. 12, 1697 / by John Howard ...</title>
            <author>Howard, John, 1647-1729?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1698</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 60 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44635</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2982</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8165</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11804047</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11804047</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49407</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44635)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49407)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 535:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The evil of our dayes with the remedy of it : a sermon preach'd at a visitation at Rothwell in Northamptonshire, Octob. 12, 1697 / by John Howard ...</title>
                  <author>Howard, John, 1647-1729?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Lawrence ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1698.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Ephesians V, 16 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Visitation sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49407:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49407:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE EVIL Of Our Dayes. WITH The Remedy of it.</p>
            <p>A SERMON PREACH'D At a <hi>VISITATION</hi> at <hi>Rothwell</hi> in <hi>Northamptonſhire, Octob.</hi> 12. 1697.</p>
            <p>By <hi>John Howard</hi> M. A. Rector of <hi>Marston Truſſel</hi> in the ſame County.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Lawrence</hi> at the <hi>Angel</hi> in the <hi>Poultry,</hi> 1698.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:49407:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:49407:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A</hi> Visitation-Sermon.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>EPHES. V. 16.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Redeeming the time, becauſe the days are evil.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>AS all the Churches under St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Care, were great Inſtances of his Wiſdom and Diligence in the Miniſtry; ſo none more than that of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſus.</hi> He had been Reſident with them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Three years together, and by God's Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing upon his Zealous and Painful Endeavours, Converted many, both <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles,</hi> to the Faith of Chriſt. At his departure from them, he left <hi>Timothy</hi> to be their Biſhop, a Man excellently qualified for that Office, and fit to carry on the Great Work which the Apoſtle had ſo happily Advanc'd. And that he might do it the better, he ſent his Firſt <hi>Epiſtle</hi> to him not long after, wherein he gave him full Inſtructions about all the Duties of his Holy Function. Yet ſome years after this, when he was Priſoner at <hi>Rome</hi> for the ſake of the Goſpel, fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing loaſt his Sufferings might diſcourage the Chriſtians at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> and conſidering alſo what Temptations they had at home to ſhake their Faith; that no means might be wanting for their further Confirmation and Perſeverance in it, he Writes this <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle</hi> to them for thoſe ends. Wherein he firſt Praiſes God for thoſe Admirable Priviledges they enjoy'd by virtue of Chriſt's Redemption, and for the Conſtancy of their Faith, Praying that
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:49407:3"/>they might Increaſe in Wiſdom and Holineſs. Then he puts them in mind of their ſinful and miſerable eſtate before Converſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and of the rich Mercy and Grace of God in delivering them out of it. To this he adds an account of the particular Grace of God to himſelf, in Calling him to the Miniſtry, in making Extraordinary Revelations to him, and ſending him to Preach among the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> the unſearchable Riches of Chriſt: whereby not onely Men, but the holy Angels too, would be further Inſtructed in the Myſterious Effects of Man's Redemption. Wherefore he Exhorts them not to faint at his Tribulations for them; and Prays for the increaſe of their Spiritual Strength, their Faith, Love and Divine Knowledge, and that they might he filled with all the fullneſs of God. And having ſpent near half the Epiſtle upon theſe Subjects, which were moſt fit to confirm and encourage them; he does in the following part of it exhort them to thoſe neceſſary Duties which the Priviledges beforemention'd do call for: Beſeeching them firſt in the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral to walk worthy of their Vocation, and then particularly directing them in their whole Behaviour towards God, and the World. And amongſt other excellent Rules, he gives them many particular Cautions, both in the fourth and fifth Chapters, againſt all the Sins of the Age and Place they lived in; arguing from the danger of them to their Souls, (notwithſtanding what ſome deceivers might ſuggeſt to the contrary,) from that great and admirable Change which was wrought in them, from the proper Fruit and Efficacy of the Holy Spirit, their Duty on the contrary, to reprove ſuch things, and the ſhame that belong'd to them, that they muſt by all means avoid thoſe Sins. And having now in many inſtances directed and warn'd them, he ſeems to ſumme up all in the Verſe before and in that of my Text—<hi>See then that ye walk Circumſpectly,</hi> &amp;c. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſee therefore how Circumſpectly, Dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently or Exactly ye walk— Which words do imply, ſeeing by the free Grace of God, and his infinite Love in Jeſus Chriſt, ye were call'd out of Darkneſs into Light; from a State of Ignorance, Infidelity, and Miſery, to that of a Divine Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, Holineſs and Salvation; ſince ye enjoy the glorious
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:49407:3"/>Priviledges Chriſt has purchas'd for you by his own Blood, for the increaſe of Spiritual Graces and Comforts in your Souls, and Security of your Eternal Happineſs; ſince you live amongſt many Adverſaries and great Temptations to Sin againſt God, whereby you would forfeit his Bleſſings and incurre his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure; — <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>— therefore look to your ſelves, that ye walk with all that exactneſs and caution which theſe things require in you, as it becomes wiſe Men to do. Which Precept is yet more brieſly comprehended in the words of my Text, <hi>Redeeming the Time;</hi> for which the Apoſtle adds this one Reaſon, inſtead of many, <hi>becauſe the days are Evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In ſpeaking to theſe words I ſhall firſt ſhew the meaning of them, and how far they concern'd the <hi>Epheſians;</hi> and then ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply them to our own caſe.</p>
            <p>The Precept here, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, would (I think) be more fitly render'd, Buying the Seaſon, For <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſignify to Buy or Purchaſe, as well as to Redeem, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is a Seaſon or opportunity, in which ſenſe time is alſo ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times uſed. This is a Metaphorical expreſſion taken from Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants who will deny themſelves, and take great care and pains, eſpecially in a difficult time, to purchaſe Goods to their beſt Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage. So the <hi>Epheſians</hi> are here exhorted to walk with the greateſt Caution and exactneſs, that as wiſe Merchants, they may purchaſe that Treaſure, the valuable Seaſon which is put into their hands, and make it their own, by the moſt prudent and pious improvement of it; and the rather, <hi>becauſe the days are Evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are two things which make the time Evil, namely, Sin and Suffering. And for both theſe it was an Evil Time, when St. <hi>Paul</hi> wrote this Epiſtle, eſpecially at <hi>Epheſus.</hi> There the <hi>Gentils</hi> were more than ordinarily Zealous for their vain Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitions, chiefly in the Worſhip of their <hi>Diana.</hi> There all thoſe Sins which the Heathens too generally liv'd in, did very much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound, and againſt which the Apoſtle does particularly warn the <hi>Epheſians</hi> in this Epiſtle. Here, in ſome of their Feaſts, they Murder'd all they met with in the Streets, and at laſt put <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy</hi> to Death, (as <hi>Photius</hi> tells us) becauſe he forbad them. Yea here, as if this was the chief Seat of the Devils Kingdom, were
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:49407:4"/>very many of his moſt profeſſed Diſciples, Magicians or Sorcerers, as appears from the great number of them St. <hi>Paul</hi> had converted, the price of whoſe Books was fifty Thouſand pieces of Silver, <hi>Acts</hi> 19.19. Beſides, here were already many falſe Teachers, as the followers of <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> the <hi>Nicolaitans,</hi> and about this time, or ſoon after, the <hi>Ebionites</hi> and <hi>Cerinthians,</hi> who endeavour'd as much as they could, to corrupt the Doctrines of Chriſt by their peſtilent Hereſies. Yea, from among themſelves aroſe ſome Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducers too, as <hi>Hymeneus, Alexander, Philetus</hi> and others, mention'd in the Epiſtles to <hi>Timothy.</hi> Which things were exactly according to the Apoſtles Prediction, <hi>Acts</hi> 20.29, 30. Where ſpeaking to the <hi>Elders</hi> of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> he ſaith, <hi>I know this, that after my departing, ſhall grievous Wolves enter in among you, not ſparing the Flock. Alſo of your own ſelves ſhall men ariſe, ſpeaking perverſe things, to draw a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way Diſciples after them.</hi> So evil were the days wherein theſe <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſians</hi> liv'd, in reſpect of Sin. Therefore the Church could not be ſecure from the other evil of ſuffering.</p>
            <p>But to ſay nothing of the ſecret Temptations of the Devil, which are common to all Chriſtians in every time and place, though they muſt be ſuppos'd moſt violent where that ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my had ſuch an intereſt to loſe, and in ſo great danger, as at <hi>Epheſus.</hi> To paſs by many other Troubles, which almoſt conſtantly at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend a ſincere Profeſſion of the Goſpel; Here the Diſciples were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes liable to Perſecution for the ſake of Chriſt, from the blind Heathens on the one hand, and the more obdurate <hi>Jews</hi> on the other. Here, as 'tis moſt probable, St. <hi>Paul</hi> and his Companions met with thoſe great Troubles, which he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains of, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.8. which preſs'd them out of meaſure, above ſtrength, inſomuch that they deſpair'd even of Life; and had the Sentence of Death in themſelves. For it is certain he was in danger at <hi>Epheſus</hi> of being carried to the <hi>Theatre,</hi> (<hi>Act.</hi> 19.29, 30.) to be devour'd there, as we may ſuppoſe, by Wild Beaſts kept for the Execution of Malefactors, and to which Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians afterwards were ſometimes expos'd. Therefore he ſayes, That, <hi>after the manner of Men,</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, according to Man, or, ſo far as was in Man's Power) <hi>he fought with Beasts at Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> 1 Cor. 15.32. And it cannot be ſuppos'd, but the Church
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:49407:4"/>muſt be always in a Suffering State, and receive daily Affronts from the Rage and Malice of ſuch Enemies among whom they liv'd; though St. <hi>Paul</hi> does not directly mention it in this Epiſtle; for this Reaſon, it may be, leaſt it might have Exaſperateed their Enemies the more againſt them; and therefore he gives only ſuch general hints to it, as this in the Text. Now becauſe they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dur'd theſe and ſome following Perſecutions, with a true Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Courage and Patience, our Saviour mentions this to their ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, Rev. 2.3. <hi>Thou haſt born, and haſt patience, and for my Names ſake haſt labour'd, and haſt not tainted.</hi> Thus it appears theſe <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſians</hi> liv'd in an evil time, both in reſpect of Sin and Suffering; and it is with relation to theſe eſpecially, that the Apoſtle Exhorts them, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to make the beſt Merchandiſe of the preſent ſeaſon, by behaving themſelves with that wiſdom and circumſpection, which ſuch evil Times did eſpecially require. And in this ſenſe it will beſt agree with what appears to be the deſign of the ſame Exhortation to the <hi>Coloſſians,</hi> Chap. 4.5. <hi>Walk in wiſdom toward them that are without, redeeming the time.</hi> That is, uſe that prudence in your Converſation towards Unbelievers, that ye may preſerve your ſelves from their ſins, and from ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering by their means, and gain upon them, if poſſible, in order to their receiving the Faith of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Now this Exhortation, and the reaſon by which it is enforc'd, do nearly concern all Chriſtians at this day, and in this Nation, but eſpecially Miniſters of the Goſpel, who, of all Men, ſhould be moſt ſenſible of the evil of the Times, as indeed they uſually feel the greateſt ſhare of it; and who have a more conſiderable and difficult part to act with relation to it than others. Therefore, in the following part of my Diſcourſe, I ſhall chiefly confine my ſelf to them. And becauſe the Apoſtle exhorts us to redeem the time, with reſpect to the evil of it, I ſhall firſt repreſent to you the evil of our preſent days, and then ſhew how we are to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem the time with reſpect to it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First.</hi> I ſhall give ſome account of the evil of our dayes, both in reſpect of ſin and ſuffering.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:49407:5"/>
            <p n="1">1. In reſpect of Sin. And here I have a very Melancholy Scene before me, and ſuch as I had rather ſecretly lament, than de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe to you, were it not neceſſary we ſhould know and conſider this dreadful evil, in order to its Cure, if it be not paſt remedy. We live in an Age and Nation, wherein too many are Monſtrouſly corrupted in their Judgment and Manners. Some are ſunk ſo far below the common reaſon and ſenſe of Mankind, as to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the God that made them, though there is a thouſand times more certainty of his exiſtence, than their own. Others will own no Religion but what is Natural, becauſe, they cannot compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend thoſe Myſteries God has reveal'd to us; and ſo they deny the Lord that bought them. Some arrogate to themſelves a Power of keeping the whole Law, and attaining Perfection and Happineſs by that means; others contend for a Chimerical Faith, that has neither grounds nor effects, as ſufficient for Salvation, how bad ſoever Men are in their hearts and converſations; and ſo make our Bleſſed Lord himſelf (as much as lies in them) a Patron of vice and wickedneſs, and his Holy Religion a pretence for the vileſt practices. What ſhall we ſay of Popery, that Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dra of errors, which have been ſo often baffled, and yet they live? Though, one would think, if the Men of that Religion would ſeriouſly conſult either Faith, or Reaſon, and that Law of Kindneſs, which is naturally written in our hearts, they muſt needs be aſham'd of their groſs Idolatry, of the many contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and abſurdities they have receiv'd, and that Cruelty practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in their Church towards all Men, that dare be wiſer than themſelves. To theſe I might add, the Dreams and Fancies of many <hi>Enthuſiaſts</hi> among us, who conceive ſuch Notions of God, and their Duty towards him, as are unworthy of his Being, and ſo far below thoſe excellent diſcoveries he has made of his Nature and Will in holy Scriptures, that their own Reaſon, as imperfect as it is, would in a great meaſure correct theſe mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes, if they would but attend to it.</p>
            <p>Now what can be the fruit of ſuch errors in Mens Minds, but a Corruption alſo in their Converſation? which indeed is very great and common amongſt us. What horrid Oaths and Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:49407:5"/>what ſcoffs at Religion and the ſincere Profeſſers of it, are heard in many places? How is the Sacred Name of God, his Ordinances and Providences deſpis'd? How are his holy Word and Miniſters Ridicul'd, and made Subjects for the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane Wit and Raillery of thoſe ſenſleſs Men, who thus abuſe the gifts of God, to his diſhonour and their own deſtruction? And does not Profaneneſs, in ſome meaſure, enter into our very Churches too? For even there we often obſerve a behaviour in Men very unſutable to thoſe Places, and the holy Duties per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd in them. What irreverence is us'd in Prayer? What indifferency in hearing the Word of God? Yea what drowſineſs is indulg'd by ſome, and what levities practis'd by others, while they are preſent at theſe Ordinances? And if the Sacred Rights of God are thus violated by ſinfull Men, it is the leſs wonder they ſhould alſo invade thoſe of their Neighbours, and that we ſo often hear of Contentions, Murders, Adulteries, Thefts, Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, Falſe-witneſs, Malicious Slanders, Revilings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and that there is ſo much Pride, Covetouſneſs and Intemperance amongſt us. To theſe I muſt add the many Rents and Diviſions in the Church of Chriſt, whereby Men do a great indignity to our bleſſed Lord himſelf, and fruſtrate, as much as lies in them, one gracious end of his dying for us, the uniting all into one body; the many Petitions alſo he made to God the Father, and the excellent Precepts he has given us to this purpoſe. And hence it is, (as well as from other cauſes before-mention'd) that the Houſes of God are ſo little frequented, his Worſhip both in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ublick and Private ſo ſtrangely neglected, and particularly the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, that holy Feaſt inſtituted by our Saviour for a Commemoration of his dying Love to us, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage us more ſtrictly in that ſervice which is perfect freedom, and to convey Spiritual Grace and Comfort to us. How is this neglected by moſt Men? as if they had no ſenſe of their Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſmal Engagements, which are here repeated, of the moſt gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious work of Mans Redemption by the death of Chriſt here repreſented, or the Intereſt and Happineſs of their precious and Immortal Souls, which would be very much promoted by a ſerious and frequent attendance on this holy Ordinance. Hence
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:49407:6"/>alſo is that almoſt general indifferency in Religion, I mean in reſpect of the great ſubſtantials of it; for there is too much Zeal in all parties for thoſe leſſer things which diſtinguiſh them from other Proteſtants. They are very fond of the occaſions and marks of their Separation from their brethren, as if needleſs di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions in the Church, which were of old condemn'd by our great Apoſtle as works of the Fleſh, had now chang'd their Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and were become means of Grace and Salvation! The intemperate heats Men have for theſe things, together with thoſe of Worldly and Carnal Affections, have almoſt exhauſted that true Zeal for God, and that ſincere Affection to one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which are the diſtinguiſhing Marks of Chriſts Diſciples. It is becauſe Iniquity does ſo abound, that the love of many is grown cold: though for this very reaſon, it ought to have been more fervent, as will appear hereafter. Thus have I mention'd ſome of the moſt common Sins amongſt us, wherein we may ſeem a parallel even to <hi>Epheſus</hi> it ſelf, when this Epiſtle was written. If the Heathens there were violent Idolaters and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors of Chriſtians, ſuch are our Papiſts too; if ſometimes they practic'd barbarous Cruelties upon any they met with, and were ordinarily very diſſolute and licentious in their Lives; we are not without inſtances of the former ſort, and do too much abound with thoſe of the latter: and our Atheiſt is ſuch a monſter as perhaps was not known amongſt them. If Errors and Hereſies did infeſt the Church then, we have ſome of the worſt of them reviv'd in our days, and have added many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to them. If there were ſome perverſe Men in the Church at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> that ſeparated themſelves, and drew Diſciples after them, theſe are far outdone by the many Schiſms and Diviſions amongſt us at this day. If the believing <hi>Epheſians</hi> were accus'd, ſome time after the writing of this Epiſtle, for having leſt their firſt love, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.4. how much more may we be condemn'd for almoſt the entire loſs of ours, and falling into a luke-warm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, like that chargd upon <hi>Laodicea,</hi> and for which our Bleſſed Saviour ſo ſeverely threatens her? We may therefore ſay of our own days, in reſpect of the Sins that abound amongſt us, as the Apoſtle did of thoſe he liv'd in, that they are Evil. And
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:49407:6"/>the more, becauſe thoſe in our days that commit the ſame Sins with the Heathens at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> have been better inſtructed than they, and proſeſs a pure and undefil'd Religion; and all wilful Sins amongſt us, are committed againſt as many gracious Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidences of God towards us, as were ever ſhew'd to any Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Our days are Evil too in reſpect of Suffering. But here I will acknowledge, to the praiſe of Gods Goodneſs and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, that we are not liable to ſuch bloody Perſecutions, as the <hi>Epheſians</hi> were daily in danger of. We live not under Laws that make our Religion a Capital Crime, or Magiſtrates that are ready to Judge and Condemn us for it to the moſt Cruel Deaths. Yea, though the Proteſtants, in ſeveral Neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Nations, have been thus barbarouſly dealt with by the Papiſts, and we our ſelves were in imminent danger of the ſame ſufferings, it pleas'd God, of his inſinite goodneſs to prevent them by an unexpected and wonderful deliverance: and now at laſt to confirm this more, and free us from many ſenſible effects of a long and dreadful War, by the Peace which is ſo happily concluded. But notwithſtanding theſe undeſerv'd effects of God's Mercy, I have ſaid enough al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready to prove one of the greateſt Perſecutions at this time, and in this Nation, that can befall good men, but eſpecially faithful Miniſters. St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> (<hi>Hom.</hi> 10.) ſpeaking of thoſe words of the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.12. <hi>All that will live Godly in Christ Jeſus ſhall ſuffer perſecution;</hi> brings in this Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, by way of Objection, When the Church is in a ſtate of Peace and Tranquility, Protected by Laws, and Defended by Princes, How then do they, who live Godly, ſuffer Perſecution? To which he Anſwers, <hi>Qui inter malos vivunt perſecutionem patiuntur; quia omnes mali perſequuntur bonos, non ferro &amp; lapidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, ſed vita &amp; moribus.</hi> They who live amongſt Evil Men, do ſuffer Perſecution; for all Evil Men Perſecute the Good, not with Sword and Stones, but by their Life and Manners. And then he Inſtances in the caſe of <hi>Lot</hi> in <hi>Sodom,</hi> whom none Perſecuted
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:49407:7"/>or Moleſted there, but only by their Wicked Lives With which, as St. <hi>Peter</hi> tells us, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> he Rack'd or Tortur'd his Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Soul from day to day. And indeed this Perſecution has been always very Grievous to Good Men. It drew Rivers of Waters from the <hi>Pſalmist</hi>'s Eyes, and made the Soul of <hi>Jeremy</hi> weep in ſecret places. Yea, for this, as well as for the Judgments it would bring upon <hi>Judah,</hi> he paſſionately wiſhes, That his <hi>head were waters, and his eyes a fountain of Tears,</hi> that he might <hi>weep day and night for them,</hi> Jer. 9.1. And none will wonder at this, that conſider how Injurious ſin is to the Honour of Almighty God, how contrary to the Temper of every Good Man, and in what danger it puts them that are guilty of eternal Damnation. And if theſe ſinners be under our own charge, our Affliction is the greater on their account. If St. <hi>John</hi> had no greater Joy, than to <hi>hear that his Children walked in Truth,</hi> nothing could afflict him more, than their defection from it. If it was the Joy and Crown, yea the very Life of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> that the Churches, under his Care, ſtood faſt in the Faith, it muſt be a matter of great trouble, and humiliation, yea ſomething like Death it ſelf to him if they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted it. Nay, if in ſome caſes, as St. <hi>John</hi> Teaches, we ought to lay down our Lives for the Brethren; that is, in a time of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution, when it may appear neceſſary for the Confirmation of them that Believe, and the Converſion of others: then their wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full continuance in ſin, or manifeſt defection from the Faith, ought to be more grievous to us than Death it ſelf. And alas! How many ſuch caſes as theſe do we ſee in our Pariſhes? Some who have been under our Preaching many years, and, it may be, receiv'd private Inſtructions from us too, are yet groſly ignorant of the plaineſt and moſt neceſſary Principles of Religion. Others who have Improv'd more in Knowledge, are notwithſtanding very looſe and ſcandalous in their Lives. Some that cannot be much accus'd, either of ignorance, or groſs Commiſſions, are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry defective in their Piety towards God, Charity towards their Neighbours, or thoſe Relative Duties they are particularly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd to. Others that would ſeem, it may be, to have a regard to all theſe, for want of a ſound and ſetled Judgment in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:49407:7"/>are eaſily impos'd on by the ſubtilty of ſeducing ſpirits, and drawn away from our Communion. Now can any thing more ſenſible grieve a Faithful Miniſter, who has the Care of thoſe <hi>Souls,</hi> and has taken much pains to Inſtruct and Edify them in the Faith of Chriſt, than to ſee them thus deſpiſe or deſert him, and hazard their own Eternal ſalvation? God has ſet us over our People as Paſtors over their Flocks, yea as Fathers over their Children. And can we be ſuppos'd the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Shepherds</hi> that are indifferent what becomes of our <hi>Flocks;</hi> or the onely Fathers that have no Compaſſion for our Children, or Concern for their Eternal Happineſs? The Care, Diligence and Watchfulneſs of all the Faithful ſervants of Chriſt, do plainly beſpeak the contrary.</p>
            <p>Therefore, though theſe unhappy Men, who thus fruſtrate our Pains with them, intend it not as a Perſecution to us, yet the Devil, who Tempts them to it, does really intend this, who knows how much it is his Intereſt, to diſcourage us in our Great Work, and he cannot more effectually do it, than by this means.</p>
            <p>But this is not the onely Perſecution which we ſuffer more than other Chriſtians, but our Holy Office, the Honour of which ought to be dearer to us than our Lives, does, at this day, ly under a very great, and almoſt General Contempt. And hence it is, that the worſt Conſtruction is ſo often put upon our Words and Actions, that many Calumnies are ſo eaſily caſt upon us by ſome, and ſo readily believ'd by others, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Thus are we Perſecuted even with Swords, though not in St. <hi>Augustin</hi>'s ſenſe before mention'd, yet in that of holy <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> who Complaining of the Malicious Speeches of his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies againſt him (<hi>Pſal.</hi> 59.) ſays, <hi>That Swords are in their Lips.</hi> I may add to theſe things the Invaſion of our Sacred Office by many, who have neither Gifts nor Opportunities to fit them for it; and therefore while they preſume to be Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, do juſtly fall under the Apoſtles Cenſure upon ſome ſuch Men at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> that they underſtand neither what they ſay, nor whereof they Affirm. I might mention alſo ſeveral other Injuries we often ſuffer as Miniſters, but it is time for me to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:49407:8"/>come to the other part of my <hi>Text;</hi> and I have been the longer and more particular upon this, becauſe the knowledge of theſe things, I will not ſay, (For who does not know them?) but a ſerious ſenſe of them will be a great ſtep toward their Cure, which I ſhall now</p>
            <p n="2">2. Conſider, in ſpeaking to the Precept in my <hi>Text, Redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the time,</hi> or Buying the Seaſon. Here therefore I muſt ſhew how we are to uſe, and improve our time, with reſpect to the Evils be foremention'd.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The Evil of Sin.</item>
               <item>2. The Evil of Suffering.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt.</hi> The Evil of Sin. And here we muſt take care,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt.</hi> To preſerve our ſelves from it. <hi>Secondly.</hi> To do what lies in us to Remedy it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt.</hi> To preſerve our ſelves from this Evil, and lead a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation as contrary to it as is poſſible. And this the Apoſtle does exhort the <hi>Epheſians</hi> to, in many particulars before my <hi>Text,</hi> and muſt be ſuppos'd to intend it in this Precept, as much as any thing elſe. There ly indeed very great Obligations upon all that Name the Name of Chriſt, to depart from Iniquity, and be followers of him, in a pious and uſeful Converſation; but eſpecially Miniſters of the Goſpel, whom he has appointed in his own ſtead, not only to Inſtruct others in the way to Heaven, but alſo to lead them in by a holy Example. And it concerns them, for the honour of God, and the ſafety of themſelves and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, to be the more circumſpect, as Sin is more common amongſt us. Therefore, if Errors and Hereſies do ſo much abound in this Nation, we ought to be more diligent in ſearching after the Truth, and conſtantly adhere to it. If others are ſo vicious in their Lives, it lies upon us to be the more Sober and Innocent, to watch carefully againſt Temptations, and to preſerve our ſelves not only from all groſs Commiſſions, but alſo (as far as may be) from the very appearance of Evil. If the Duties of Religion, both
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:49407:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>towards God and Men, are ſtrangely neglected, by many that would go for Chriſtians, let us be the more zealous and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant in the performance of them. If a great Indifferency in Religion has obtain'd amongſt all Orders of Men, and there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main but few Sparks of that Holy Fire of Zeal and of Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which makes our Service an Acceptable Sacrifice to God; let us by all means, endeavour to Revive and Cheriſh it in our ſelves, and make it the more intenſe, by reaſon of that Coldneſs with which we are encompaſs'd. For in ſo General a Defecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from the Life and Power of Godlineſs, What will become of the Honour of God and his Cauſe in the World, if we deſert it, or are cold in it? And what greater Judgments than any we have yet felt, may reaſonably be expected for this Apoſtacy, if the Righteouſneſs of our Lives, and Sincere Importunity of our Prayers, do not prevent them?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly.</hi> We muſt do what we can to remedy this Evil. And what I have already mention'd, the Holineſs of our Lives, will do very much towards it. For this will naturally create a Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration for us in the Minds of Men, and give us more Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority in the uſe of other Means. It will provoke them that have any remains of Piety in their Hearts, Confirm ſuch as are wavering in the Faith, and half perſwade thoſe who were before Averſe to Religion, of the Truth and Excellency of thoſe Doctrines, which they ſee have had ſo much power upon our ſelves, and produce ſuch amiable fruits in our Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation. For there is a beauty in Holineſs, which every eye (one would think) may in ſome meaſure diſcern. There is a greatneſs in Self denyal and contempt of the World, which commands admiration; and there are thoſe charms in Humility and condeſcention, in meekneſs and compaſſion, in a civil and courteous behaviour towards all Men, that muſt needs abate ſomething of the moſt inveterate prejudices againſt the ways of God, and win very much upon thoſe that are in ſome meaſure prepar'd for them. Yea, they will give us ſuch an intereſt in their affections, as will make them more apt to conſider, and receive good Inſtructions from us. And which is more than all this, our faithfulneſs to God in ſuch an holy
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:49407:9"/>Converſation will qualify us for his bleſſing upon the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours we uſe for the good of others.</p>
            <p>The other means neceſſary to remedy the Evil of Sin, are eſpecially theſe following.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. We muſt endeavour to convince thoſe that are guilty.</item>
               <item>2. We muſt warn and inſtruct others.</item>
               <item>3. We muſt pray to God for his bleſſing upon theſe things.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. We muſt endeavour to convince thoſe that are guilty.</p>
            <p>In order to which it will be neceſſary.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. To uſe the fitteſt arguments with ſuch as err in Judgment.</item>
               <item>2. To reprove thoſe that are guilty of other Sins.</item>
               <item>3. To ſhew kindneſs both to the one and the other, as there may be oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. To uſe the fitteſt arguments with ſuch as err in Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. The Principal of theſe, if he be properly reckon'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, is the Atheiſt; but I think his Error is rather in the will. Some Men (if they deſerve that name) have ſo much improv'd their Natural Affection to Sin, by indulging them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in it, that they cannot with any comfort think there is a God, who will Judge and Reward them according to their deeds, and therefore heartily wiſh there were no ſuch Being. Which ſeems to be the <hi>Pſalmiſt's</hi> meaning, when he ſays, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 14.1. <hi>The fool hath ſaid in his heart</hi> (that is, in the deſires of it) <hi>that there is no God;</hi> and in the next words tells us whence this Atheiſm proceeds, <hi>They are corrupt, they have done abomin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able works.</hi> And therefore while they talk as if Atheiſm was their belief, it may be, theſe bold Efforts againſt Heaven are
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:49407:9"/>intended only for ſome excuſe of their Wicked Lives. For it is hard to think, that they who have the leaſt remains of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in them, ſhould be able to reſiſt all the plain and moſt ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible evidences of God's Exiſtence. While they open their eyes, they ſee as many proofs of it, as there are beings in their view, or Motions and Properties in thoſe Beings: and if they ſhut them, every thought of their Hearts is a demonſtration of it. So that one would think, a Man muſt go out of the World, and from himſelf too, before he can be altogether inſenſible of the Divine Exiſtence. But if his mind can be ſo far beſotted with Senſuality, as to loſe all ſenſe of it, it is in vain to uſe any rational Arguments to convince him. Some indeed have taken pains to anſwer this fool according to his folly, in ſhewing the incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtence of his dreams and fancies; it may be, with reſpect to that Rule, <hi>Prov.</hi> 26.5. that he might be no longer wiſe in his own conceit: and have excellently ſet before him the moſt conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Arguments of God's Being and Providence. But he that can ſhut his eyes againſt all the viſible Teſtimonies of theſe things, will probably have very little ſenſe of the force of their Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Yea, it is like, this way of dealing with him, will make him but the more conceited of himſelf. For while he is treated as a Man of Reaſon, he will take encouragement to ſhuffle off all that can be ſaid againſt his Principles; and there is little queſtion but he will find as good pretences for it, as for his former un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief. But I confeſs theſe diſcourſes are of great uſe to others, to confirm their Faith, and aſſiſt them upon every obſervation of thoſe things, from whence the Author's arguments are taken, to be more ſenſible of God's preſence with them, and of the dominion he exerciſes in the World. One would think the moſt proper Argument to work upon this ſenſualiſt, (if he be capable of any) would be from the delight and ſafety of true Religion, <hi>whoſe ways are ways of pleaſantneſs, and all her paths are Peace.</hi> Of which, if the little Reaſon he has left will not convince him, he might at leaſt make Trial, and preſer that courſe which he finds to be beſt. But why do I ſpeak of arguing with a Beaſt? For if it be Religion which diſtinguiſhes Man from the brute Creatures, as ſome great Authors have reſolv'd, the Atheiſt
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:49407:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>who is fallen from it, muſt be reckon'd amongſt them. And I think the Wiſe Man does direct the proper method of deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with him, when he ſays, <hi>A whip for the Horſe, and a bridle for the Aſs, and a rod for the fools back, Prov.</hi> 26.3. It is ſenſe, through the pleaſure of Sin, that has betray'd him to this Error; and it muſt be Senſe, through the ſmart of Suffering, that will cure him of it. 'Tis therefore the Magiſtrates work chiefly to convert this Apoſtate. And we cannot ſufficiently lament it, that while Humane Laws are ſo jealous of every invaſion of our own Rights, and ſo ſeverely executed upon them, the moſt bold and dreadful Impieties againſt God, whoſe cauſe we ſhould prefer a thouſand times before our own, do eſcape Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>The next I ſhall mention are the Socinians, who have ſhew'd ſo much confidence of late, in publiſhing and defending their notions, as if they might appeal to the reaſon of Mankind for the Juſtice of them. Theſe Men ſeem to own Revelation in the general, but at the ſame time aſſert ſuch Principles as over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw it; but whether this be owing moſt to their Reaſon or their Piety, I leave it to themſelves to determine. Some a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, who I believe have been far from their Opinions, have notwithſtanding paid a great deference no their Reaſon. But though they themſelves have ſet up this Idol in oppoſition to Almighty God, to judge of his deep and holy Myſteries, 'tis pitty and others ſhould fall down and Worſhip it. And had theſe Men but carefully examin'd, what they have blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ador'd, they would have been of a very different Opinion. The fitteſt way, I think, to deal with theſe Adverſaries, is, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of magnifing their Reaſon, to ſhew them the weakneſs of it. Which ſeems no hard matter to do, if they had but Humility enough to think it fallible. For, when there is an equal Evidence of the Divine Authority of ſeveral books of Scripture, what reaſon is there they ſhould receive ſome of theſe, and reject others? If they cannot deny there are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>accountable Myſteries in the connection and diviſibility of the parts of matter, in motion, in the union of the Soul with the Body, and many other things, whoſe exiſtence they are aſſur'd
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:49407:10"/>of; with what Reaſon do they deny theſe in Religion, which has for its object an Infinite God, all whoſe Attributes muſt needs be incomprehenſible to ſinite Beings, and the whole intercourſe between him and our Souls, as to the manner of it, above the reach of an Humane Judgment? Spiritual things are certainly further remote from our underſtanding, than thoſe that are Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural; and yet theſe Men of Reaſon will allow no Myſtery in them, while they are forc'd to acknowledge very many in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. To this we may add their rational way of Interpreting Scriptures, whereby they would make thoſe Divine Oracles ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pear as void of good Senſe and Reaſon as themſelves. But neither theſe, nor any other efforts of their exalted Reaſon, want any confutation from me, ſince they have been ſufficiently baffled of late, as well as formerly, by ſeveral worthy Authors. But it become's all true Miniſters of the Goſpel, (and indeed every good Chriſtian) that acknowledge and adore the ever-bleſſed Trinity, together with the Infinite Wiſdom, Juſtice and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God, in the Incarnation of our bleſſed Lord and Saviour both God and Man, and that great Redemption he hath wrought for us; that are ſenſible of Original, as well as Actual Sin, and what need the World had of that meritorious Sacrifice, offer'd by our glorious High-Prieſt, in his own Body upon the Croſs, to reconcile them to God, and the imputation of his Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for their Juſtification: It becomes us, I ſay, upon all fit oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, to declare our abhorrence of ſuch Antichriſtian Principles, as thoſe of the Socinians are, which ſtrike at the very foundation of our Religion, and were doubtleſs inſtill<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d into Mens minds by our great Adverſary, in order to the Deſtruction of it. But we know it is defended by a ſtronger than he, who will one day call this Enemy, and all his adherents, to an account for theſe things. And here I cannot forbear mentioning another deteſtable notion of theſe Men, or their Friends, lately publiſh'd, that there is but one Article of Faith propos'd in the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, as neceſſary to be believ'd in order to Salvation; namely this, that Jeſus Chriſt is the Son of God. But theſe diſcoveres don't perceive that he who made this confeſſion, <hi>Acts</hi> 8 37. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd all other Articles of our Faith before; and that this, rightly
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:49407:11"/>underſtood, does include and ſuppoſe all the reſt. What a ſtrange degree of Pride and confidence is this, that makes Men dare to vent new notions in Religion! As if all the Learned, Wiſe and Holy Men, from the Apoſtles time till this Age, never rightly underſtood the conditions of Salvation! And then, how will this reflect upon the Wiſdom or Sincerity of the ſacred Writers of the New Teſtament, yea of the Holy Ghoſt himſelf, if by them he has ſo obſcurely deliver'd truths of this moment, that they could never be rightly underſtood for aboue ſixteen hundred years to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether? But the deſign of theſe Men is to diſparage the Holy Scriptures, and therefore they deal with them as with a Syſtem of Natural Philoſophy, that is liable to be chang'd in every Age, as new truths are diſcover'd, or pretended ſo in that Science. It be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoves us therefore with all the Zeal of Good Chriſtians and Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Miniſters, to repreſent, as there may be occaſion, the Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs and danger of ſuch Innovations, and prevent, as much as lies in us, the growth of them amongſt our People. And we ſhould do the ſame alſo againſt all other falſe Notions in Religion, common in theſe days, which I have not time now to mention. I ſhall therefore only add ſomething in the general, concerning thoſe leſſer differences in Opinion amongſt Proteſtants, which are the cauſes of Diviſions in the Church. Theſe I think, might, in a great meaſure, be reconcil'd if they were once but rightly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, and fairly argued by the Parties concern'd in them; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially if that mutual condeſcenſion could be us'd on all hands which the Rules and Intereſt of our Religion do require. And it muſt be always remember'd, that when we have to do with Perſons Erroneous in Judgment, (if there be any hopes of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincing them) all our arguments muſt be us'd with great kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and compaſſion towards, them, that if poſſible we may gain upon their affections, and then their Judgment will much ſooner ſurrender to us. For, to accuſe a Man of Errors in this kind, ſeems moſt directly to reflect upon his Wiſdom, which Men have uſually a greater opinion of in themſelves, than any thing elſe; and therefore it had need be done in the ſofteſt and moſt obliging manner. Beſides, this way o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ling with Men, ſhews we have a reſpect for them, and gives th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m alſo a greater opinion of our
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:49407:11"/>Piety and Wiſdom, as well as of our good will towards them, on which accounts they will be more apt to conſider our arguments, and yield to them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We muſt Reprove the ſins of Mens lives; ſuch as I before mention'd, and all others that appear to us: as the Apoſtle ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horts, <hi>verſ.</hi> 11. <hi>Have no fellowſhip with the unfruitful works of darkneſs, but rather reprove them.</hi> This is required of all Men, as a neceſſary act of Charity to our Neighbours, Lev. 19.17. <hi>Thou ſhalt not hate thy Brother in thine heart; thou ſhalt in any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſe rebuke thy Neighbour, and not ſuffer ſin upon him.</hi> But Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters muſt eſpecially do this with all Authority, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.15. and with all long-ſuffering, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.2. Yet theſe Precepts do not oblige us in reſpect of all Men; for we are Caution'd not to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove a Scorner, <hi>Prov</hi> 9.8. That is, one ſo harden'd in ſin, that he will deſpiſe the Means we uſe to reform him, and return evil upon us for our Charity to him. Such our Bleſſed Saviour calls <hi>Dogs</hi> and <hi>Swine,</hi> and has left us this Rule concerning them, Mat. 7.6. <hi>Give not that which is Holy unto the Dogs, neither caſt ye your Pearls before Swine, lest they trample them under their feet, and turn again and rent you.</hi> But I think there are few that we ought to account ſuch, till we have made ſome trial of them, and Admoniſh'd them according to our Saviour's Command, both Privately and before Witneſs; and, if this courſe proves ineffectual, they are to receive the Cenſures of the Church. But we muſt not always Reprove Men ſo ſoon as they have ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, or we come to the knowledge of it, but when we have moſt reaſon to hope for the good effect of it; and, in ſuch a manner, as is moſt ſuitable to the temper and condition of thoſe we have to deal with in order to it. For, next to the Glory of God, the main end of Reproof is the gaining of our Brother; which, if it can be done by a diſcreet uſe of this means, the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Happineſs of his Soul will be ſecur'd, the Honour of God moſt promoted, and our own Conſciences beſt diſcharg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by it.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:49407:12"/>
            <p n="3">3. We muſt ſhew Kindneſs to all evil Men, as there may be occaſion for it; what Enmity ſoever they may bear to us: ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our Saviour's Precept, Mat. 5.44. <hi>I ſay unto you love your enemies, bleſs them that curſe you, do good to them that hate you, and pray for them which deſpightfully uſe you and perſecute you:</hi> and this he enjoyns as a matter of great advantage to our ſelves, as in the <hi>Verſe</hi> following, <hi>that ye may be the children of your Father which is in Heaven.</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> (after <hi>Solomon</hi>) gives us a like Precept, in order to the Spiritual good of our Enemy, Rom. 12.20. <hi>If thine enemy hunger feed him; if he thirſt, give him drink; for in ſo doing thou ſhalt heap coals of fire on his head.</hi> Which is a <hi>Metaphor</hi> taken from <hi>Metals,</hi> that are ſooneſt melted when fire is caſt upon them. And therefore the Senſe of theſe words ſeems to be, by theſe means thou ſhalt ſoften thine Enemy, and reconcile him to thee. For though they will bear another Senſe, yet this is moſt probably intended by the Apoſtle, becauſe he adds in the <hi>Verſe</hi> following, <hi>Be not over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of evil, but overcome evil with good.</hi> Now if an Enmity conceiv'd againſt us, upon the account of the Goſpel, may be thus conquer'd, a Perſon is thereby reconcil'd to Religion, and ſo brought into the way of Salvation. And what greater Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive can we have to ſhew kindneſs to our Enemies, next to the Glory of God, and the Happineſs of our own Souls, than the probability of convincing them of ſin, and bringing them to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance and Reconciliation with God by this means? This Kindneſs will alſo give a great advantage (as was before hint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) to ſuch other menas as we uſe to convince any Sinners. It will add ſtrength to our Arguments with them that err in judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and make all our Reproofs and Inſtructions come with greater Force and Authority upon others.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As we are to uſe theſe Means to convince the Guilty, ſo we muſt alſo Warn and Inſtruct others, that they fall not into the ſame Errors, either in Judgment or Practice. To this end it will be neceſſary, with all plainneſs and earneſtneſs, to Repreſent to our People the Sinfulneſs of our Nature, the evil and danger of Sin, the many Temptations we are encompaſs'd with, and the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:49407:12"/>Judgments of God denounc'd againſt Sin, both in this and a fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture State. And on the other hand, the natural goodneſs of God to his Creatures, his Infinite Love in Chriſt to all that truly Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent of their Sins, believe in the Lord <hi>Jeſus,</hi> and obey his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, the Comfort and Happineſs of a Holy Life here, and the Glorious Salvation which will be the Reward of it hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. To theſe things we muſt add particular Cautions againſt thoſe Sins and Errors which are moſt common amongſt us, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the dangerous conſequence of them. And all this with ſuch a Senſe and Zeal, as may convince them we believe it our Selves, that we have a true Compaſſion for their Souls, and deſire of their happineſs. But our greateſt care ſhould be employ'd about the moſt hopeful part of our Charge, the Children in our ſeveral Pariſhes, to Inſtruct them in the Principles and Rules of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, that they may know whatſoever is neceſſary to be Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd and Practis'd in order to Salvation. To which end, we muſt not only take care that they are perfect in the Form of their <hi>Catechiſm,</hi> but endeavour, by explaining it familiarly to them, to make them underſtand it, as far as they are capable; that the Fear of God, and a Senſe of their Duty to him, poſſeſſing their Hearts betimes, may preſerve them from the ſins of the preſent time, and fit them to do eminent Service to God hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. And we have the greater reaſon to hope for this ſucceſs, becauſe the habits of Sin being but weak in them, are more eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſubdu'd by good Inſtructions, and their Minds not yet pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſs'd with other Notions, will receive the deeper and more laſting Impreſſions from them; and not only for the Informing their Underſtanding, but Governing their Converſation too, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that of the Wiſe Man, Prov. 22.6. <hi>Train up a Child in the way he ſhould go and when he is old he will not depart from it.</hi> So that if we have but little ſucceſs in Reforming the preſent Age, this will conduce much to the Innocence of the next, and thereby to the Glory of Almighty God, the Proſperity of his Church, and the Eternal Salvation of many Souls. But here we ſhall need all Aſſiſtance from their Parents too, who, by that In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt they have in them, and being ſo much with them, may do
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:49407:13"/>this Good Work, with greater Advantage than our ſelves, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially if it be ſeconded by their good Example.</p>
            <p n="3">3. To theſe Means, we muſt add our daily and fervent Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to that God, who ſearches all Hearts, and can change them as he pleaſes, who is Light and Truth it ſelf, and can reform all the Errors of Mens Minds; who ſees and hates the Ungodly Converſation of ſome, and the Lukewarmneſs of others amongſt us; who is ready to bleſs all proper Means, that are Zealouſly and Prudently uſed for the Correcting Mens Errors, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming their Hearts and Lives; and with whom the Effectual Fervent Prayer of a Righteous Man availeth much: that he would be pleas'd to direct and aſſiſt us in all our Endeavours to theſe Ends, and Crown them with his Bleſſing.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I am to ſhew how we are to redeem our Time, or make the beſt uſe of it, with reſpect to the evil of Suffering: And this I ſhall do in Two Particulars.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. We muſt carry our ſelves prudently towards the Enemies of Religion.</item>
               <item>2. We muſt bear patiently thoſe Sufferings we meet with for the Sake of Chriſt.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. We muſt carry our ſelves prudently towards the enemies of Religion; that we may not give them any occaſion to offer Indignities to us; according to the Rule our Saviour gave his Diſciples, Mat. 10.16. <hi>Behold I ſend you forth as Sheep in the midst of Wolves: be ye therefore wiſe as Serpents, and harmleſs as Doves.</hi> The enmity which many bear to Religion, will make them apt to take up any new Pretences againſt it; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they will the more curiouſly obſerve our Converſation, and be ready to charge us with the leaſt appearance of evil in it.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:49407:13"/>How much does it concern us therefore, to the take the Apoſtles Caution in the <hi>Verſe</hi> before my <hi>Text</hi>— <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. See therefore how circumſpectly or warily ye walk; and that Col. 4.5. <hi>Walk in wiſdom toward them that are without, redeeming the time.</hi> Thus we ſhall make the beſt uſe of our time, with reſpect to them, if we alſo ſhew that kindneſs to them, which was mention'd before.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We muſt bear patiently thoſe Sufferings we meet with for the ſake of Chriſt, in doing our duty. Though I confeſs that Perſecution which comes upon us from the bad Principles and Converſation which comes upon us from the bad Principles and Converſation of Wicked Men, whereby the Honour of God and the Intereſt of Religion ſuffer ſo much in the World. and many Souls are in ſo great danger of eternal Damnation; will juſtify our Impatience more then any other. To be quiet and eaſie in the obſervation of theſe things, is the effect, not of a great, but of a ſenſſeleſs Mind; and to be ſatisfy'd before we have try'd all Veans to remedy ſuch evils, would argue a great want of Charity to the Souls of Men. Notwithſtanding, even while we have a due Senſe of their danger, and are zealouſly attempting to reſcue them out of the Snare of the Devil; yea, if we have try'd all fit Means in vain, or with but little ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, we muſt not be very much diſcouraged on this account. For though the natural Seed uſually ſprings up quickly, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Labours of the Husbandman in a few Months, yet the ſpiritual Seed, the word of God, with which we inſtruct and warn our People, does often produce its effects many years after. Therefore let us here take the advice which the Wiſe Man gives with reſpect to works of Charity, Eccleſ. 11.6. <hi>In the Morning ſow thy Seed, and in the Evening withhold not thine hand, for thou knoweſt not whether ſhall proſper, either this or that, or whether they both ſhall be alike good.</hi> But whatſoever the ſucceſs of our holy endeavours may be, we our ſelves ſhall not loſe the reward of them. For if a faithful Miniſter has cauſe to complain with the Prophet, Iſa. 49.4. <hi>I have labour'd in vain, I have ſpent my ſtrength for nought and in vain:</hi> he may add with him too, <hi>yet
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:49407:14"/>ſurely my Judgment is with the Lord, and my work with my God.</hi> And v. 5. <hi>Though Iſrael be not gather'd, yet ſhall I be glorious in the eyes of the Lord, and my God ſhall be my ſtrength.</hi> As for other Afflictions which befall us for the ſame cauſe, we ought to bear them as perſons that have ſufficient motives to encourage and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort us under them all. If Men deſpiſe our Profeſſion, we know that God has highly honour'd it. And indeed there is nothing in our holy Office below (the greateſt Men, ſhall I ſay? or rather) the moſt glorious Angel to perform. The ſubject of our Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is the Word of God, wherein are all the Treaſures of Wiſdom and Grace; the end of it is to ſave Men from Eternal Miſery, and bring them to a ſtate of Eternal Happineſs. The Sacraments we Adminiſter are Pledges of the Love of God in Chriſt to Penitent Sinners, Engagements upon them to be Faithful to their great Lord, and means to convey thoſe Divine Virtues which will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able them to be ſo. When we viſit the Sick, it is to inſtruct and Pray for them, that they may be fitted for Glory, if they dye, and to ſerve and honour God more, if they recover. When we bury the Dead, we do an act of Charity both to them, and to the Living. To us God has given Authority to bleſs his People in his Name, yea to Remit and Retain Sins. All which things are ſo far above the contempt of Men, that the holy Angels might envy us in the doing of them, if they were capable of ſuch a Paſſion. And it is not for any meanneſs in our Office, but for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reaſons, that God has not employ'd thoſe Glorious Creatures in it. The Work does indeed highly deſerve them, but we could not bear their Miniſtrations in it: and God has committed this Treaſure to earthen Veſſels, to Perſons that are mean and frail, and of ſuch narrow capacities as our ſelves, that the glory of its Succeſs may be wholly his own. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.7. Therefore if igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant and ſenſeleſs Sinners will deſpiſe ſuch an Office, it becomes us, with St. <hi>Paul,</hi> to magnify it; and let them conſider how much the Eternal God himſelf is concern'd in this caſe. For he that deſpiſeth, deſpiſeth not Man but God, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.8. And our Saviour tells the ſeventy Diſciples, and in them all Miniſters of the Goſpel, Luke 10.16. <hi>He that heareth you, heareth me; and he
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:49407:14"/>that deſpiſeth you, deſpiſeth me: and he that deſpiſeth me, deſpiſeth him that ſent me.</hi> Having therefore ſuch partners in this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, it behoves us rather to glory in it, than be diſcouraged by it. Whatever other Affronts or Injuries a faithful Servant of Chriſt receives, he may be comforted, not only from the former conſiderations, but the caſe of our bleſſed Lord himſelf; who came into the World upon the moſt gracious deſign that was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver carried on in it; who was perfectly Innocent, and continually went about doing good; and yet endur'd the worſt Perſecutions of all ſorts, from thoſe very Men whoſe Souls he came to ſave. Therefore a Patient enduring of Afflictions, will make us in a great meaſure conformable to the Lord Jeſus, and thereby work out for us an exceeding and Eternal weight of Glory. It will alſo at preſent ſecure our own Peace and Tranquillity in deſpight of any that would diſturb it, and ſo make us better Merchants of the preſent Seaſon, in Redeeming it from ſuch diſturbing thoughts and complaints as thoſe injuries are apt to provoke in us.</p>
            <p>Thus have I ſhew'd, in ſome part, how we muſt uſe our time with reſpect to the Evil of it; and that there is moſt need of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeming the time, when the days are Evil, to preſerve our own Innocency, to reform the Age we live in, to bear our Sufferings patiently, and to promote the Honour of God in the World. To which I might add ſeveral other Reaſons, as,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. It is then moſt Praiſe-worthy.</item>
               <item>2. Then it is eſpecially neceſſary to prevent the Judgments of God, denounc'd againſt Sin, particularly that which at laſt came upon <hi>Epheſus</hi> (as well as the other Churches of <hi>Aſia</hi>) for not making a good uſe of their opportunities and means of Grace; namely, the removal of the Goſpel from them, according to our Saviours threatning, Rev. 2.5. <hi>Remember from whence thou art fallen, and Repent and do the firſt Works; or elſe I will come unto thee quickly, and will remove thy Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick out of his place, except thou Repent.</hi> Which Judgment we have alſo too much reaſon to fear, and therefore ought to uſe our beſt care and diligence to prevent it.</item>
               <item>3. The improveing ſuch a
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:49407:15"/>Seaſon will be more abundantly rewarded, both in this and a future Life.</item>
            </list>
            <p>I might alſo draw ſeveral inferences from what has been ſpoken, but the time will not give me leave. Therefore I ſhall only add, that ſeeing this is a buſineſs of the greateſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance, and very difficult too, ſeeing our time is very ſhort and uncertain, our own abilities inſufficient for ſuch a Work, and we live in the midſt of many and great Temptations to abate our Zeal and diligence in it; we ought to look the more carefully to our ſelves, and uſe the beſt means to fit us for it. Let us there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Redeem what precious time we can from all unneceſſary avocations, and employ it diligently in Reading, Meditation and Prayer. Let us confer often with one another, for our mutual aſſiſtance and encouragement; and let us endeavour always to preſerve ſuch a Temper of Mind, free from Worldly Cares and other diſtracting Paſſions, as will make us capable of higher im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provements by theſe means, and engaging more entirely in the work of the Lord, for the greater honour of his holy Name, the better ſucceſs upon the Souls of our People, and a more glorious Reward to our ſelves, hereafter in the Heavens.</p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>PAge</hi> 12. <hi>l.</hi> 20. <hi>r.</hi> teaches us. <hi>p.</hi> 14. <hi>l.</hi> 23. <hi>r.</hi> in it. <hi>p.</hi> 15. <hi>l.</hi> 5. <hi>r.</hi> Zeal and Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>p.</hi> 18. <hi>l.</hi> 29. <hi>r.</hi> Magnifying. <hi>p.</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>l.</hi> 21. <hi>r.</hi> differences.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <p>THe True Intereſt of a Nation: or the Duty of <hi>Magiſtrates, Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters</hi> and <hi>People,</hi> in order to the further Settlement and Proſperity of theſe Kingdoms. A <hi>Sermon</hi> Preach'd at the Aſſizes held at <hi>Bucking<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, July</hi> the 5th. 1692. By the ſame <hi>Author.</hi> Printed for <hi>J. Lawrence,</hi> at the <hi>Angel</hi> in the <hi>Poultry.</hi> 1693.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
